Guide to the Caltagirone family photographs ARC.305
Brooklyn Historical Society
Caltagirone family papers and photographs
circa 1900 to 1999
Brooklyn Historical Society
Caltagirone family
Caltagirone, Marian (1929-)
ARC.305
0.75 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes
The collection consists of photographs of the Caltagirone and related families (especially the La Rocca family), dating from circa 1900 to 1999, as well as related materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marion Caltagirone, circa 1993-2000.
Arrangement
Generally arranged chronologically and by type.
Biographical note
Marian Caltagirone was born to Agostino and Concetta "Tina" (La Rocca) Caltagirone in 1929. Her father was born in Sicily circa 1900, and immigrated to New York in 1920. Her mother was born in New York circa 1908 to Gerlando and Phillippine La Rocca. Gerlando was also born in Sicily, and his family had immigrated to New York by 1905. Both Gerlando and Agostino were barbers by trade. Marian had one brother, John Caltagirone, who was born in 1939. The La Roccas resided on Marcy Avenue, in both the Williamsburg and Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhoods of Brooklyn. Starting in the 1940s, the Caltagirones lived at 107 Navy Walk in the nearby Fort Greene Houses. By the 1960s, members of the family had relocated to 1553 39th Street in the Borough Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. Marian attended Mark Hopkins J.H.S. 148 and the Eastern District High School as a teenager; she later graduated from Brooklyn College in 1977. Agostino passed away in 1985. Concetta lived in the Augustana Lutheran Home for the Aged (1680 60th Street) from 1986 until her death in 1990.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of photographs of the Caltagirone and related families (especially the La Rocca family), dating from circa 1900 to 1999. Photographic formats include black-and-white prints, color prints, tinted photographs, tintypes, and negatives. Thematically, the photographs document a 20th century Italian-American family in Brooklyn, including their residences, celebrations, recreation, and family life. The photographs were collected by Marian Caltagirone.
The earliest photographs in the collection are portraits of members of the La Rocca and Caltagirone families, dating from the 1900s to the 1930s. These include seven photographs mounted on buttons (or pins), some of which are hand-tinted and/or backed with mirrors.
The Fort Greene Houses, where the Caltagirones resided, are extensively documented (interiors and exteriors). These photographs date from the 1940s to the 1960s. Other locations documented during this time include Fort Greene Park, Prospect Park, Prospect Park Zoo, Tompkins Park, the Coney Island and Brighton Beach neighborhoods of Brooklyn, the playground at Avenue F and McDonald Avenue, barber shops (in Brighton Beach and at East 15th Street and Cortelyou Road), and various schools (Eastern District High School, Mark Hopkins J.H.S. 148, P.S. 122, St. Barbara's High School, and the Manual Training High School).
The photographs depict a number of family celebrations and holidays, including Christmas, birthdays, weddings, graduations, first communions, and reunions. The collection includes a number of wedding thank you cards with portraits of the brides and grooms (circa 1930s to 1970s).
Later photographs document the Augustana Lutheran Home for the Aged (1680 60th Street) and snow-covered streets in the Bath Beach neighborhood of Brooklyn (1995).
In addition to the Caltagirone and La Rocca families, the following surnames are represented in the collection: Conti, Sferlazza, Brennan, Giacomaggio, Piscitello, and Biancardi.
Residences documented in the photographs include 512 Marcy Avenue, 107 Navy Walk (in the Fort Greene Houses), 1553 39th Street, 247 Bay 17th Street, 57 Hammond Avenue (Passaic, New Jersey), and homes on Middleton Street and Bleecker Street (Brooklyn). Other institutions documented in the collection include St. Barbara's Roman Catholic Church (Bushwick), the Holy Ghost Church (17th Avenue and 43rd Street), Brooklyn College, the Silver Star Resaurant (18th Avenue and 62nd Street), and Linden Hill United Methodist Cemetery.
In addition to photographs, the collection contains one folder of papers relating to Marian Caltagirone's education at Brooklyn College. That file includes course work, transcripts, certificates, and other documents, dating from 1963 to 1980.
Also included are two memory books regarding Concetta and Agostino Caltagirone, information pertaining to their social security and old age benefits, Marion Caltagirone's Junior High, High School, and Brooklyn College diplomas, and a baby book celebrating the birth of John Caltagirone (son of Concetta and Agostino), as well as some of his hair.
Related Materials
Rainone-Morra Family Papers (BCMS.0022) Papapietro family photographs (V1990.028) Angela Boglioli Oppizzi papers (2014.014) Joseph and Raffaela Tarone Salvagna photographs and papers (2015.033)
College students |z New York (State) |z Kings County; First communion |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Winter storms |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bath Beach (New York, N.Y.); Postcards; Sicilian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Retirement communities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nursing homes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Families |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Navy Walk (New York, N.Y.); Brighton Beach (New York, N.Y.); Herbert Von King Park (New York, N.Y.); Parks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Weddings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Catholics |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Christmas |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Borough Park (New York, N.Y.); Barbers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Barbershops |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Kensington (New York, N.Y.); Snow removal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Commencement ceremonies |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tintypes (prints); Photographs; Negatives (photographic); Cards (information artifacts); Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Color prints (photographs); Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Black-and-white prints (photographs); Fort Greene Park (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn College; Brennan family; Biancardi family; Piscitello family; Linden Hill United Methodist Cemetery (New York, N.Y.); Augustina Lutheran Home for the Aged (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Holy Ghost Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Sferlazza family; Conte family; Conti family; Giacomaggio family; Caltagirone family; St. Barbara's High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Barbara's Roman Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); J.H.S. 148 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Caltagirone, Marian (1929-); Caltagirone, Marian (1929-); LaRocca family; Prospect Park Zoo (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.). Eastern District High School; P.S. 122 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Photographs, circa 1900-1930s (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1940-1951 (Box 1)
- Wedding thank-you cards with photographs, circa 1940s - 1970s (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1953-1965 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes a 1957 image of Ebbets Field.
- Photographs, 1966-1999 (Box 1)
- Photograph albums, 1986-1992 (Box 1)
- Note regarding photographs, 1997 (Box 1)
- Marian Caltagirone Brooklyn College material, 1963-1980 (Box 1)
- Concetta and Agostino Caltagirone materials (Box 2)
- Marian Caltagirone diplomas, 1944-1976 (Box 2)
- Marian Caltagirone certificates, 1933, 1943 (Box 2)
  Baptism certificate (1933) and certificate of Gallantry in Giving to the New York War Fund (1943).
- John Caltagirone baby book and hair, circa 1939 (Box 2)
- John Caltagirone tooth care certificate, 1948 (Box 2)
- "Triumph of Man" record from World's Fair, 1964-1965 (Box 2)